<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tutorial | Joe Woodward]]></title>
  <link href="http://joewoodward.github.io/blog/categories/tutorial/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://joewoodward.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-16T01:02:28+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://joewoodward.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Joe Woodward]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Octopress on GitHub Pages in 15 minutes]]></title>
    <link href="http://joewoodward.github.io/blog/2013/06/02/blogging-with-octopress-and-github-pages/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-02T23:21:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://joewoodward.github.io/blog/2013/06/02/blogging-with-octopress-and-github-pages</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Octopress is a framework designed by Brandon Mathis for Jekyll, the blog aware static site generator powering Github Pages. To start blogging with Jekyll, you have to write your own HTML templates, CSS, Javascripts and set up your configuration. But with Octopress All of that is already taken care of.</p></blockquote></p>

<p><img src="/images/octopress_logo.png" title="Octopress" ></p>

<!-- more -->


<h4>What Do You Need?</h4>

<p>You only need a few things to use Octopress' awesomeness</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://git-scm.com/downloads">Git</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/downloads/">Ruby 1.9.3</a> (I highly
recommend using <a href="https://github.com/sstephenson/rbenv">rbenv</a> to
handle multiple ruby versions)</li>
<li>A text editor</li>
</ul>


<h4>Setting Up Octopress</h4>

<p>Octopress' source code is stored on github so all we have to do is clone the repo.</p>

<pre>
$ git clone git://github.com/imathis/octopress.git my_blog
</pre>


<p>You will need to change into the directory that you
cloned Octopress into. If you are using rvm to manage your ruby versions, you will
be asked if you want to trust the .rvmrc file, you should answer yes.</p>

<pre>
$ cd my_blog
</pre>


<p>Next we need to install a few dependancies, Octopress uses the bundler
gem making the process very simple. If you don&rsquo;t already have bundler,
install it.</p>

<pre>
$ gem install bundler
</pre>


<p>Note: if you are using rbenv you will need to run rehash for bundler to
work.</p>

<pre>
$ rbenv rehash
</pre>


<p>The bundler gem uses a gemfile to store a list of dependancies, all you have to do
to install them run the bundle install command.</p>

<pre>
$ bundle install
</pre>


<p>Now the dependancies are installed you are almost ready to view your
new blog. You can install the default theme or <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/wiki/3rd-Party-Octopress-Themes">download a different
theme</a>.
To install the default theme run</p>

<pre>
$ rake install
</pre>


<p>You can view yoursite locally by running rake preview and visiting
<a href="http://0.0.0.0:4000">http://0.0.0.0:4000</a></p>

<pre>
$ rake preview
</pre>


<p><img src="/images/first_look.png"></p>

<h4>Deploying Your Blog To GitHub Pages</h4>

<p>To host a site on <a href="http://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> you need to
create a <a href="https://github.com/repositories/new">new GitHub repo</a> with
your github user name like this <code>username.github.io</code></p>

<p>Github Pages uses the master branch of your repo the in the same way a
web server uses the public directory. It servs the files to your github url
<a href="http://username.github.com.">http://username.github.com.</a>
This means you need to work on the source for your blog in the source branch and commit the generated
content to the master branch. Octopress has a rake task that
helps you set all this up.</p>

<pre>
$ rake setup_github_pages
</pre>


<p>This will</p>

<ul>
<li>Ask you for your Github Pages repository url.</li>
<li>Rename the remote pointing to imathis/octopress from ‘origin’ to ‘octopress’</li>
<li>Add your Github Pages repository as the default origin remote.</li>
<li>Switch the active branch from master to source.</li>
<li>Configure your blog’s url according to your repository.</li>
<li>Setup a master branch in the _deploy directory for deployment.</li>
</ul>


<p>Now that you have setup deployment you can generate your site and deploy
it.
Run rake generate and then rake deploy. This will generate your blog files and copy them over into
the _deploy directory, add them to git and push it to your master branch
on GitHub.</p>

<pre>
$ rake generate
$ rake deploy
</pre>


<p>Within a few minutes you should recieve an email from GitHub confirming
your blog has been published. Your blog&rsquo;s live, go to your GitHub Pages
URL, <a href="http://username.github.io,">http://username.github.io,</a> to check it out.</p>

<p><img src="/images/first_deploy.png"></p>

<h4>Using Your Own Domain Name</h4>

<p>If you would like to use your own domain name rather than username.github.io, you have to create
a CNAME file in the source directory containing your domain name.</p>

<pre>
$ echo 'your-domain.com' >> source/CNAME
</pre>


<p>Your DNS needs to be pointing to the right place</p>

<ul>
<li>If you are using a domain like <code>your-domain.com</code> you should
configure an <strong>A record</strong> pointing to <code>204.232.175.78</code></li>
<li>If you are using subdomains like <code>blog.your-domain.com</code> you
should configure a <strong>CNAME record</strong> pointing to
<code>username.github.io</code></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
